

Contact

- Rua Dep. Raimundo Leal, s/n, Jd. Eldorado, Cond. Vitale Residence, BL 6, AP 2 - São Luís, MA, Brasil. CEP 65.066-635.
- **(** +55 (98) 99223-4811
- fabio23gt@gmail.com

Skills

PHP

Laravel | Lumen | Symfony | Zend **Docker** | Podman

Kubernetes | Docker Swarm **AWS** (EC2, ECS, S3, EKS, EBS, RDS, SQS, ElastiCache)

Golang

DigitalOcean | Linode | Heroku

Debian | Ubuntu Server (Linux)

GitHub Actions (CI/CD) | Jenkins

NGINX | Apache

GIT

HTML | CSS

Bootstrap | Tailwind CSS

JavaScript | Node.JS | Webpack

React JS | Next.js | Nest.js

MySQL | MariaDB | PostgreSQL

Redis

MongoDB

Studying

RabbitMQ | Kafka

Rust

Fábio Assunção 30 years old

Software Engineer

About

With over 15 years of software development experience, I have worked on diverse projects, including open source collaborations and automating development processes. My expertise lies in PHP and Node.js, with additional knowledge in Golang, Python and Java. I am skilled in various cloud providers such as AWS, GCP, Azure, as well as Docker, Kubernetes, and other virtualization technologies. Throughout my career, I have led teams, undertaken projects, and enjoyed sharing knowledge through lectures and courses.

Professional Experience

Senior Software Engineer

VITRINE RETAIL | February 2023 - present

At Vitrine Retail, a Visual Merchandising startup focused on fashion retail, I work as a Senior Software Engineer, primarily focused on API development, supervising other developers' work, creating technical documentation, and planning.

Senior Software Engineer

ZENVIA | August 2022 - February 2023

During my brief tenure at Zenvia, I worked as a Senior Software Engineer and focused on improving backend development processes, as well as CI/CD. This included defining development guidelines for Node.JS and PHP in legacy projects. I dockerized some services to improve local development and enable container deployment. Additionally, I played a crucial role in maintaining and developing features for legacy projects. As part of my work, I conducted workshops on Docker for development and production, as well as shared best practices in PHP and Node.JS development.

Tech Lead

MPRJ | April 2021 - April 2022

At MPRJ, I worked as a Technical Leader and played an important role in coordinating the Development, QA, and Requirements Analysis teams in the Software Factory Contract 074/2021 between MPRJ and my company Codions Tecnologia.

Tech Lead

VAT Tecnologia | May 2017 - April 202

During my second stint at VAT Tecnologia, I was invited to work as a Technical Leader through my company, Codions Tecnologia. In this role, I led the development, customization, and implementation of licensed e-learning systems for the governments of the Amazonas, Pará, and Maranhão states,

as well as higher education institutions such as the Federal University of Amazonas and the State University of Amazonas, the Amazonas Education Media Center, and private companies.

Among my responsibilities, I highlight the quality audit of projects developed by other developers, requirements gathering, system analysis and programming, technical documentation preparation, developer training, program and system testing, as well as cloud and on-premise infrastructure provisioning, mainly on AWS and Digital Ocean.

Consulting Software Engineer

Light Tecnologia | June 2016 - April 2017

At Light Tecnologia, I worked as a third-party Technical Consultant through my company Codions Tecnologia. During this period, I played an important role in the development and implementation of software for the legal area, which was used by all notary offices in the state of Maranhão, as well as integrations with databases from CNJ, Federal Police, and other institutions. My responsibilities included quality auditing of projects developed by other developers, requirement gathering, systems analysis and programming, technical documentation, developer training, program and system testing, as well as cloud infrastructure provisioning and resource migration from AWS to GCP.

Founder & Tech Lead

Codions Tecnologia | April 2016 - August 2022

In 2016, I founded Codions, a software house that represented my first challenge as an entrepreneur. I had the opportunity to work on a variety of projects, regardless of their size, assembling teams and winning contracts with the Brazilian government through bids. Due to the small size of the company, I had to step out of my comfort zone and learn about business management, projects, contracts, and people management, which represented a significant challenge but provided me with valuable learning. During my time as the company's leader, I remained connected to the technical area, continued studying, learned new programming languages, and had more contact with DevOps.

Senior Web Developer

VAT Tecnologia | February 2015 - April 2016

After being promoted at VAT Tecnologia, I started my role as a Senior Web Developer, focusing my efforts on developing and analyzing systems for academic management, as well as maintaining a human resources control software. Additionally, I expanded my experience with Virtual Private Servers (VPS), worked on provisioning the LAMP/LEMP stack on Debian and Ubuntu Server platforms, and participated in load balancing using NGINX. I also began studying PaaS, AWS, and Kubernetes, further expanding my knowledge in the technology field.

Mid-level Web Developer

VAT Tecnologia | October 2013 - February 2015

During that period, I worked as a Mid-level Developer and took on small leadership roles within the team. I was one of the responsible for the adoption of Clean Code concepts and application of some of the SOLID principles in the projects my team was working on. In the same year, there was a need for portable development environments, which led me to study Vagrant, virtualization concepts, and later on Docker.

Junior Web Developer

VAT Tecnologia | October 2012 - October 2013

In my first formal job as a programmer, I worked as a Junior Web Developer and was responsible for assisting in the maintenance of some internal systems that were initially developed with the LEMP stack. During this period, I had my first contact with on-premise server infrastructure and started studying Linux Server, VPS, and virtualization.

Freelancer

January 2008 - June 2012

During my first experience in the technology field, I worked as a freelance Web Developer and focused my efforts on developing institutional websites, content portals, and small web systems for local businesses.

Computer Instructor

Prefeitura Municipal de Bom Jardim - MA | March 2007 - December 2007

During the school year of 2007, I had the opportunity to teach basic computer skills to elementary school students in municipal public schools in Bom Jardim, Maranhão. As a teacher, my goal was to empower students to use essential computing tools such as Windows, Office Suite, and Corel Draw, so they could apply this knowledge to their school activities and future careers.

Education

2012 - 2016 Computer Science

Faculdade Pitágoras

Languages

Portugues Nativo English Intermediate

Courses Taught

Getting Started with Golang

FLISoL, Universidade CEUMA, São Luís - MA, 2018

Developing RESTful APIs with Laravel and Docker

VAT Tecnologia da Informação, Manaus - AM, 2018

Flutter: Creating Native Apps for Android and iOS

FLISoL, Universidade CEUMA, São Luís - MA, 2019

What does a front-end web developer do?

Practical Course on HTML, CSS, JS, Git, DNS Configuration, and CI/CD using GitHub Actions, GitHub Pages, and Vercel.

Inova Maranhão, Online, 2021

Lectures Given

Technology-Mediated Education

Feira de Estágio e Emprego do MA, Sebrae Multicenter, 2014

JavaScript, a World Beyond the Browser

Google I/O Extended, UNDB Centro Universitário, 2015

Technology-Mediated Education and the Job Market in IT

Il conferência do Google Developer Group, São Luís - MA, 2015

Security and Privacy in the Era of Social Networks

Semana Nacional de Ciência e Tecnologia, Sebrae Multicenter, São Luís - MA, 2018

Security and Privacy in the Era of Social Networks

FLISoL, Universidade CEUMA, São Luís - MA, 2019

Links

GitHub: https://github.com/fabioassuncao

Linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/fabioassuncao

Timeline: https://fabioassuncao.com/timeline